每个人生都有一些 最难忘的时候
Every one has special times in their lives
我最难忘的事
My greatest memories
50多年前在中国的一些日子
is the few short days I spent in China more than 50 years ago
那片饱受战火的土地
I'll never forget the land lavished by the war
那群世界上最苦难的人民
or the valiant Chinese people
那些我一生见到过的
who faced the challenges in their incredibly hard lives
最勇敢无畏的战士
with unwavering courage and spirit.
那些窑洞和黄土地
The cave dwellings
那些东方的古庙
the ancient temples built on the foundation of silt and clay
还有那条世界著名的黄水河
and the magnificent Yellow River.
谢谢 不客气
Thank you You are very welcome.
1943年
In 1943
我在第14航空担任飞行员
I served as a bomber pilot in the United States air force
秋天的一天
One autumn day
为了准备大规模轰炸
We were on a long distance recon flight
日军在中国辽宁的军工厂
Our mission was take aero-pictures of Japanese factories in Liaoning
我和罗伯特上尉一起奔袭 去执行侦察任务
We complete our mission and headed back
拍照很顺利，任务已经完成 于是我们返航
罗伯特建议把飞机上的炸弹 留给日本人
Robert wanted to bomb the Japs right then and there.
而我认为更重要的是 将胶卷安全带回去
Me? I wanted to bring back the film safely.
但罗伯特仍坚持，这我理解
I did understand Robert's hatred of the Japanese, though
因为他哥哥前年死在珍珠港
His only brother had been killed in Pearl Harbor.
正在这时他的机会来了
His opportunity had come.
欧文，你看看是哪国的驱逐舰
Owen, whose warship do you think that is?
这还用问 在这片海域只有日本军舰
The only boats down there are Japanese
我要下去干掉他 你守着你的胶卷吧
I gotta go bomb them, you take care of the film.
小心点，我掩护你
Good luck, Rob, I'll cover you.
我们两面夹击吧
Let's get down on both sides.
好
OK
罗伯特，跳伞
Robert, jump
快要坠海了
His falling down!
要为罗伯报仇
This is for Robert
不…
No...
女士们先生们
Ladies and Gentleman
本次航班预计在15分钟后 降落在北京首都国际机场
We will be landing in Beijin in 15 minutes.
北ㄊ的地面温度24摄氏度
The ground temperature is 24 Degrees
请旅客们系好安全带，收起小桌
Please fasten your seatbelt
将座椅靠背调到正常位置
Straighten your seat back
卫生间停止使用
The lavatories are temporarily closed.
各位先生女士…
Ladies and gentlemen...
莫西！莫西！
上帝
God!
小孩子
Boy...
帮帮我
Help me
帮我
孩子
boy
小孩子
Boy
"Foreign soldiers help Chinese people fight the Japs.
照像机
Camera
不要动
Don't move
你好吗
How do you do?
你好吗，欧文先生
How do you do, Mr. Owen?
你怎么知道我的名字
How did you know my name?
你现在已经安全了
You are safe now
我们是中国军人
You are with the eighty rout army.
八路军
The eighth rout?
对
Yes
得快走，他现在自己能走吗
We have to move on, is he able to walk by himself?
你能走吗 可以
Are you able to walk? Yes
在这种山沟里会出现一个 懂英文的人真是奇迹
It was a miracle to meet an English speaking girl in such a small village.
就这样我被这群 陌生的中国人救活
So I was rescued by a group of Chinese soldier by the eighth rout army
开始了我第二次生命
我遇到的是一支 插向敌后的八路军部队
They had managed to penetrate deep into the Japanese territory.
当时四周全是日军
We were surrounded on all sides by the Japanese.
指挥官决定抽出四个人 将我护送回他们的根据地
So the commander assigned four soldiers to escort my back to the base.
领导的是个黑脸汉子
The young man leading our group was a dark faced fellow
不爱说话
with few words.
好像对我的出现很不满意
I looked unsatisfied with my presence.
安小姐曾是北平城里 一所医科大学的学生
An-Jeh is a medical student in Beijing.
战争爆发后，她参加了军医
She resolved to join the eighth rout army while the war was breaking out.
这次安排她参加护送 一是可以照护我的伤
Because the medical expertise and her English speaking skills
更重要的就是她会一点英语
She was assigned to accompany me.
我感谢上帝 给我派下来这个天使
It seemed that God had sent me an angel
我作梦也没有想到 会这样来到了长城之上
I couldn't believe that I was crossing the great wall of China.
这是世界上最伟大的奇迹之一
One of the greatest wanders of the world.
它将引导我走过这片 神奇的土地
would lead me to a fascinating land.
谢谢
Thank you
我在中国待了四年 所以我的中国话，一点点
I lived in China for 4 years so I can speak a little Chinese
这个，好看
This is very pretty.
他说你的衣服很漂亮
He said that your outfit looks great.
我想在美国会很流行的
I think it would be popular in America.
在外国也许是一种 很时髦的穿法
This would be popular abroad.
你在哪里买的
Where did you buy it?
我说错了什么
Did I say something wrong?
在我们这儿 男人出远门的时候
In China, when men leave home
女人会给他们缝一个红肚兜
Women will make them a red apron.
为的是保佑亲人一路平安的
As a good luck charm.
东方人不喜欢别人 问起家里的事，对吧
You Orients don't like it when people ask about your family, do you?
过了河就到了分区了
The division is right across the river.
刚才他说什么
What did he say?
他说我们已经进入 安全地区了
He says, we are in the safe zone now.
安全地区 没错
Safe zone? Yeah.
我只看见那里…很有意思
I only saw...interesting.
安琪儿
Angel
请叫我安洁
Please call me An-Jeh.
安琪儿
Angel
你在我危难的时候救了我
You saved my life.
是上帝派来的 就是我的安琪儿
You're my angel sent from heaven.
经过三天的急行军
After 3 grueling days on foot,
我们终于快要到目的地
We neared our destination,
八路军的军分区了
Military command post of the eighth rout army.
三天中，走过了长城 翻过了太行
看到了一贫如洗的村庄 和建在半空中的宇宙
passed poverty stricken villages and temples built on cliffs
老乡
Homey
黑子
Darkie
你好…
Hello...
你好
Hello
再见
Goodbye
不能再等了
We can't wait any longer.
得离开这儿了
We have to go
也许他正带人来接我们呢
Maybe he is already on the way
已经过了约定的时间了
He is late
只要他还活着就一定能找到 部队
If he is alive he will find the base
但如果他被俘了呢
But what if he got caught?
那他也不会说的，我了解他
He won't tell, I know him
你知道鬼子的酷刑吗
Do you know how the Japs Torture the prisoners?
我们藏在这里已经三天了
We have been in hiding for three days.
由于日军突然扫荡
And no villagers in the military base
军分区所在地的村庄 没有一个人活下来
had survived the attack of the Japanese
黑子派了一个战士 去寻找游击队
Darkie sent a soldier to search for the guerrilla
到今天也没有回来
And that soldier hadn't come back yet.
他很重要 还带着日军重要的情报胶卷
He's got important information on him
所以不能让他落在鬼子手里
We can not let the Japs get to him
欧文先生 明天我们就要离开这儿了
Mr. Owen, we leave here tomorrow
明白
I understand
本来我们的任务 是把你送到这儿来
Our mission was to get you here.
下面由分区派队伍送你过黄河
The division will assign someone get you cross the Yellow River.
过黄河
Cross the Yellow River.
对，过了黄河就是根据地了
Yes, the base is right across the river
是延安吗
Is it Yian-An?
是的
Yes
我知道
I know
可是现在只有我们 来送你过黄河了
Now we have to help you cross the Yellow River.
OK，我会游泳，你呢
OK,I can swim, and you?
我可以带你游过去
I can help you swim across
游过去
Swim
黄河
The Yellow River.
为什么不能，我会划艇
Why not? I can row
黄河的浪会比 科罗拉多的浪大吗
The waves here cannot be bigger than those in Colorado.
到了你就知道
You'll see.
这是什么宝贝
What is this?
这么说我们明天就到延安吗
We will arrive in Yian-An tomorrow?
明天
Tomorrow
走山路顺利的话也要三天
We must hike for 3 days.
安琪儿，我有话要说 你们是好人
Angel, there is something I have to say you are good people
但不懂军事，要过黄河
But you know nothing about military. You want to cross the Yellow River.
应该走这条公路 一天就能到达
You have to go along the highway, that will only take a day.
这是敌战区，不能走大路
This is occupied territory, we can not use the main roads.
我有重要的情报要送回去
I have important information for the base.
不能跟着你们
I cannot stick with you.
在山沟里钻来钻去
and walk around in the mountains.
不钻山沟，你还能飞过去
You mean you want to fly there?
你们不是真正的军人
You are not real soldiers.
在山沟里钻来钻去
You walk around in the mountains.
打不赢这场战
你说啥
What did you say?
我还会飞的，一定会
I WILL fly again.
来，去把他们叫醒
Wake them
黑子
Darkie
goodbye
他说要走公路
He says he wants to take the highway
延着公路追
Chase them along the highway
安琪儿，黑子…
Angel, Darkie...
他回来了
He is back
这是日本的车子
This is the car of the Japanese
快下来，我们可以一直开到 香格里拉去
Come on down, we can drive all the way to Shangrilla
这家伙快要捅娄子
He is going to get us into trouble.
看看我拿到什么
Look what I got.
你们在这里等着，俺下去看看
You guys wait here, I'll down and check
快上来
Come on
幸运的一天
We don't have all day.
欧文，日本人在你后面
Owen, the Japs are behind you.
不能让鬼子捉了去
Can't let the Japs get them.
你留下
You stay here.
快过来
Come on
还等啥呢
What are you waiting for?
走
Go
不
No
走
Go
由于我的失误 我们失去了一个朋友
It was my fault that the soldier died.
这也使我知道
And I now understood
我与他们之间存在着 许多的不同
the differences between us.
而在日军佔领区的作战 是一种特殊的战
谢谢
Thank you
黑子决定带我们回他的家乡
Darkie decided to take us to his home town
那里离黄河很近 他准备从那里渡河
near the Yellow River, we crossed the river in secret there
那里有一个神秘的名字 “神泉寨”
The town had a mysterious name, they called it "fairy spring village".
不见
I don't want to see them.
寨主
Chief
你先去看他们又想要干啥
Go and see what they want.
希望你早日跟我们站在一起
We wish that you can be on our side.
孙二爷，咱们那批货你还得 多关照
Mr. Sun, please take care of our cargo.
三炮呀，你还在打光棍啊
Sanpao, are you still a bachelor?
要不跟我过这边来吧 女人可有的是啊
Come with me, we got a lot of women here.
好…
OK...
我们寨主是不会亏待你的
Our chief will treat you right.
明天老地方过河
We cross the river tomorrow as usual.
咱们这土头土脑的地方 哪里来的洋人啊
How can there be a foreigner here.
装蒜
Don't play dumb with me.
搅了我一场好戏
Ruined a good play for me.
谢谢
Thank you
那就是我家
That is my home.
过了这山沟
Cross here.
就是神泉寨
You will get to the fairy spring village.
黑子 爸
Darkie Father.
你怎么回来了
What are you doing back?
咱们的人要过黄河
We want to cross the Yellow River
花花，你不是天天想你爹吗 见了怎又躲呢
Huahua, it's your dad don't be afraid.
叫什么
What's your name?
花花
Huahua
大大…洋大大给我的
The foreign uncle gave me
花花，怎么要人家的东西呢 还回去
Huahua, give it back
不…
No...
你这孩子怎不听话呢
You don't listen to me?
黑子，这是我的表
Darkie, this is my watch
送给她，你不可以管
I gave it to her, this is none of your business.
我是他爹
I am her father.
那就谢谢洋大大
Say thank you
谢谢洋…大大
Thank you
好了…不
早上爷爷叫你干啥来着
What did grandpa wanted you to do?
捉蠍子
He told me to get scorpions.
捉蠍子干啥来着
Why?
给洋大大治伤
For Foreign uncle's wounds.
治好伤干啥去
Why?
打鬼子
Fight the Japs.
那就不要送了
You don't have to see us off.
留步…
Please don't see us off...
那就不要送了，下次再来
Please visit us again.
到我们温泉洗个澡 包治百病
We can take a bath in the hot spring, it is very healthy.
花花，干什么呢
Huahua, what are you doing?
捉蠍子
I am looking for scorpions.
捉蠍子干啥
Why?
治伤
To heal wounds
你爷爷伤了啊
Is your grandpa wounded?
我不告诉你
I am not telling you
吃…
Eat...
可好吃的
It is very tasty.
这些西方人认为 公鸡才吃的虫子
I once saw a rooster ate a scorpion
在中国人那里 却被当做神奇的药物
But in China people eat them as medicine.
可是令人惊奇的是第二天 我的炎症就消除了
The next day, my inflammation was gone.
我们把衣服弄脏了 妈妈要打屁股了
We got dirty, your Mom will spank you.
怎么啦
What's wrong?
我妈妈死了
My Mom is dead.
对不起
I'm sorry.
后来我才知道
I learned later,
三年前，日军到这里扫荡
That his home town was attacked by the Japanese three years earlier
为了实验一种 新的毒气弹的性能
To test the effectiveness of the newly invented gas bomb
就在村里随意抓了一百多人 关进一座紂里
More than a 100 villagers were captured and locked in a temple
花花的妈妈和哥哥也在里面
Among them were Huahua's mother and brother.
后来黑子找到了妻子的尸体
Shortly after, Darkie found his wife's body.
从她身上取下了一件遗物
He removed her red under garment
带着它参加了八路军
And carried it with him as he rejoined the eighth rout army.
洋大大
Foreign uncle...
我还去捉好多蠍子 等你回来吃
I will get more scorpions for you
黑子，三年不见 你还能在我面前得色了
Darkie, it has been three years now you grow cocky on me?
三炮
Sanpao
黑子，乡里乡亲的 回来怎么不见一面就走了
Darkie, you want to leave without visiting me?
咱们的事单说，跟他们没关系 你放他们过去
What's between us stays between us, let them through
都带回去
Get them.
一起走吧，小妞
Come with us, sweetie.
二小姐
Miss, It's you
你探的什么信，说是去抓仇家
what kind of informer are you? You said you are going to bring me my foes,
抓出个洋人来不说 还抓出个女儿来
And you bring me a foreigner and my daughter?
这些年没了音信 原来你跟了八路
Haven't heard a word form you, now you are with the eighth rout?
谁打鬼子我就跟谁
I'll stay with whoever fights the Japs.
放着书不好好读
I wanted you to study
跟着起什么哄
Not to make trouble
读书
Study?
日子鬼子他们让我读书吗
You think that the Japs will let me study?
那你也不能和我断了音信啊
That is no reason for not contacting me
我还是你爹
I am, after all, your father.
我不认投敌的人做父亲
The minute you teamed up with the enemy you no longer are my father.
我没投敌 我没给日本人干过事
That is not right, I never worked for the Japanese.
你现在正在为鬼子干事
You are working for the Japs right now.
好了
OK
你立刻放我走
Let us go this instance.
或都把我交给鬼子去 讨个好价钱
Or you can turn me in to the Japs, get a handsome reward.
二小姐，寨主是疼你呀
Miss, chief did it all for you.
卢沟桥一开火 寨主就让俺到北平去接你
As soon as the war started, chief sent me to get you.
谁知道你早就没影儿了
But you were long gone.
你说这些年
Do you know
寨主费了多大心的心思 打听你的下落
Chief was looking for you everywhere
这下好了，二小姐回来了 大家也可以放心了
now you're home, we no longer have to worry.
要不还是先请二小姐回去休息
Miss, would you like to take a rest first?
请吧，二小姐
This way please.
她这些年跟八路心都跑野了
She has gone wild with the eighth rout.
麻烦不在这儿，我的寨主
This is not the problem.
咱们抓住洋人的事情 日本人马上就会知道
The Japanese will know that we caught the foreigner in no time
昨天孙翻译递过话来 日本人一定要活口
the translator said that the Japanese wanted him alive.
说是要弄到洋人飞机上的 啥秘密
said that they want to know some secret of the guy's plane.
这会儿二小姐 也辈在这个事情里头
Now that miss is involved.
这私通八路的罪
ganging up with the eighth rout is a crime.
要是把洋人交给日本人
but if we turn the foreigner in...
可落个汉奸的恶名
Than we become traitors
你没忘记三年前的事吧
You still remember what happened 3 years ago?
日本人可是敢灭了 咱们全寨人的命
The Japanese will wipe us out with little hesitation
真没想到，咱俩儿还是同乡
I never thought that we came from the same neighborhood.
没啥儿光采的
There is nothing be bragging about.
你父亲会把咱们儿 交给鬼子吗
Will you father turn us in?
安琪儿
Angel
我要去见日本人
I want to see the Japanese
什么
What?
我去投降
I will surrender
这一切事情都是我引起的
I caused all these
你们都是好人 为我去死我会很不安
You are good people, I don't want you to die for me.
现在已经没有希望了
It is hopeless now.
我，你，还有你
Me, you and you
都已经尽了一个军人 最大的职责
Have all fulfilled the duty of a soldier.
我们的武器也没有了
We lost our weapon.
可以无愧的停止抵抗
We can stop fighting with a clear conscience.
按照日内瓦公约 受到战俘的待遇
And be treated according to the Geneva convention as a POW.
你个孬种
You whimp!
做为一个失去武器的美国军人
I am an US soldier without weapon.
可以选择光荣的投降
I can choose to surrender.
日本人要抓的是我
The Japanese are after me.
你们因此有可能得到自由啊
You can all go free.
日本人有你想的那么公道吗
You think you can reason with the Japanese?
你可是亲眼看见 他们是怎么对待老百姓的
You saw what they did to the villagers
我不是老百姓
I am not a villager
我是军人
I am a soldier.
我也是军人
I am a soldier, too.
我要把你送到根据地去
I have to get you to the military base.
这是给我的军令
These are my orders.
在没有接到新的命令之前 我就不许你去投降
Till I get any further instruction, I forbid you to surrender
欧文先生
Mr. Owen
我知道你们把生命 看得高于一切
I know that you think life is the most valuable thing on earth
并不把尽职后的投降看做耻辱
and don't think surrender after doing your job is a disgrace.
但在我们这里
But we,
宁可失去生命 也不能失去军人的尊严
we will rather die than to live in shame.
只要还有一个子弹 我也不会停止抵抗
Even if there is only one bullet left, I will not stop fighting.
可现在我们不能无谓的 失去生命
But will can not lose our lives in vain
生命
Iife
只有你的生命是生命吗
You think only your life is precious?
你以为我们的人就可以白…
You think that we shall...
白白的为你送死吗
give up our lives for yours?
放开他
Let go of him
不要打
Stop fighting
二小姐
Miss
你难得回来
Since you are back
明儿去你娘坟上加把土吧
You can go and visit your mother's grave tomorrow.
你先歇吧，有啥儿事明儿再说
You take a rest, we'll talk tomorrow.
让我住这儿，你就不怕我跑了
Don't you worry that I will run away?
既然回来了 当然应该住自己的房
You should stay in your own room.
这些年我一直不让人动这儿
I never let anyone but you come in here
既然回来，干啥儿还走
You are home, don't ever say about leaving.
放心 要跑我会跟他们一起跑的
don't worry, I won't leave without them
我有时想，应该再抱你一次
I often thought that I should hug you one more time.
可一转眼，你已经大到 不能抱的个头儿了
But you are too old for that now.
你真要把他们交给鬼子
You really want to turn them in to the Japs?
日本人这次动静很大 要抓那个洋人
The Japanese want the foreigner
我不能把╝鹤 引到咱们儿寨子里来
I have to take care of the whole village.
当年就是为了一个人 全寨搭进去30来口
We lost 30 people for just one man
至于黑子那是咱家的世代仇人
Darkie has been our foe for years
带我回牢子去
Put me back to the prison.
一个女娃儿和两个男人 住一块儿不是个样
A girl shouldn't be staying with two guys
我是军人，天天就这个样儿
I am a soldier, I do this everyday.
穿这身衣服你是个兵
With uniform, you are a soldier,
脱了这身衣服你还是我女儿
But without it, you are my daughter.
当初就不该送他去上洋学
I should never have sent her to school.
事已至此 只能是以后慢慢再调理她了
There is nothing to be done now, I will deal with her later.
头痛的事，那俩怎么了
What about those two?
寨主，女儿是亲人，洋人是外人 黑子是仇人
She is your daughter, but those two have nothing to do with you.
外人不值得用全塞的人命去换
We don't have to die for the outsider
而仇人
And our foe...
黑子是咱安家的世仇
Darkie is our sworn enemy.
是世界上有他没我 有我没有他
There can only be one of us.
放心，这次他落在咱手里 我知道该怎么办
Don't worry, I know what to do
只是洋人
But the foreigner...
明天孙翻译 要我陪着日本人去洗温泉
The translator, Mr. Sun want me to take the Japs to the hot spring tomorrow.
你看能不能这样
How about this...
你这先把黑子给结果了
You take care of Darkie
等到差不多的时候 再把洋人的事告诉日本人
And I wait till the time is right, tell the Japs about the foreigner.
等日本人来了，黑子已经死了
When the Japs arrive, Darkie will be dead.
而洋人…
And the foreigner...
黑子啊
Darkie
是我啊，我来看你来啦
It's me, I come to visit you.
这些年我寻你寻的苦啦
I have been looking for you for so long
黑子，你自个儿送上门来了
Darkie, and now you come to our doorstep.
有本事你放我出去 咱们儿一对一
Let me out, let do one-on-one.
要你进来也行
Or you can come in.
黑子
Darkie
你们赵家害我失了男身 你还记得吗
You guy made me lose my masculinity, do you remember?
过去的仇家往后不能再打了 如今日本人…
That's in the past, but not the Japs...
少废话
Shut up
我已经熬了半辈子光棍了 能这么一笔就勾消吗
You forced me into celibacy, how can I forget that?
有报有还，老天开眼啊
Now it is you turn, there really is a God.
明儿个爷有公事 今天就在这儿给你送行
I am busy tomorrow, so I think I just drop by and say goodbye.
妈妈…
Mother...
闪开
Go away
我要见你们寨主
I want to see your Chief.
老爷他出去了
He is not here for the moment.
去哪儿了
Where did he go?
那我们一块儿的两个人呢
How about the other two?
也带走了
He took them with him.
自古欠钱还钱，欠命还命
You got to pay what you owe.
我们安家七条人命 你们赵家还欠一条
Your family took seven lives of ours, and now we take one of yours.
今天请你补齐了吧
Today we will settle this.
咱们都快成了亡国奴了 俺真为你丢人
We are losing our country, and you are thinking about settling old debts?
国难和家仇是两码儿事
These are two completely different matters.
你把美国人先放了 咱们的事情跟他关系
You let the American go this has nothing to do with him
洋人的事就不用你管了
Don't worry about the American.
小姐，你要的衣服
Miss, your clothes.
你出去吧，把门关上 我要换衣服
Go and close the door, I want to change.
太君们，快点啊
Come on gentlemen.
太君，我们这是神泉 洗了以后保治百病
Bathing in the hot spring is very healthy.
小姐
Miss
小姐跑了
Miss is gone.
安琪儿
Angel
别担心
Don't worry
他们不敢碰我
They won't touch me.
去把她拉下来 是
Go get her down. yes, sir.
谁敢动我
Don't touch me.
谁都别动
Everybody freeze
把他们解开
Untie them.
你想看我死在你面前吗
You want to see me die?
我数到三就拉
I count to three and then I'll pull.
一
二
把马牵来
get the horses.
干得漂亮极了
Well done Angel, well done
只要有人向我们开枪 或都追赶我们
If anyone shoots at us or chases us...
我就拉下这下它
I will pull.
本来是用来对付鬼子的
That was meant for the Japs.
没想到
I never thought...
用在您这儿了
I will be using it under such circumstances.
这手儿 只有我的女儿能玩出来
Only my daughter is able to do such a thing.
孙翻译，你要的洋人 我给你抓住了
Mr. Sun, I got you your foreigner.
太君，太君
Mister...
太君
Mister
不过这下子日军已知道 我们的下落和我们的目的
By this time the Japanese knew our position and our goal.
把这一带的黄河渡口 全都封锁了
And they blocked all the crossing the to Yellow River.
爷爷把我们 藏进了一座深山古庙
Grandfather hid us in an ancient temple deep in the mountain,
老和尚是他童年时的好友
Because the monk was a friend of his.
安置好我们后 黑子就再次出去找游击队了
After he got us settled in, Darkie left to search for the guerrilla again.
我和安琪儿就先留了下来
Angel and I stayed at the temple.
安琪儿带着我每天为老和尚 挑水，扫院子
Every day we carried water swept the yard for the old monk.
说这是他们的习惯
She said it was their custom.
战争似乎已经离我们 很遥远了
Within the walls of the temple, the war seemed far away.
在小岛，松林 和东方文化的神秘气息中
I was lost in the mysterious ambiance of the Oriental culture. The birds and the evergreen were our companions.
这里成为了 我和安琪儿的伊甸园
Angel and I had our own little paradise
我惊叹东方文化的古老和灿烂
Angel told me much of the long standing oriental culture
安琪儿给我讲了许多 里边的故事
Her stories of illusion
有幻想，浪漫还有爱情
of romance, war and love were magnificent.
爷爷和花花常来看望我们
Grandpa and Huahua visited me often.
每次来都是我们的一次节日
Every visit was like a holiday.
爷爷说万一没有别的办法 就用这些东西游过去
Granap said we could cross the river by carrying calabashes.
他知道一个可以游过去的地方
He knew a spot where we can swim across
中国人很聪明
He was true China man, extremely wise.
他们总是能想出各种 奇妙的方法去解决问题
They have ways finding ingenious solutions to their problems.
安琪儿，我的肚子累了
Angel, I am tired.
饿，你说我饿了，不是累了
You mean that you are hunger
花花的蝎子 不但完全治好我的伤口
The scorpions not only healed my wounds
也使我变成了一只 爱吃虫子的公鸡
but also turned me into a rooster that loved to eat insects.
开飞机
Fly an airplane.
去打鬼子
To fight the Japs.
我是中国人民的朋友
I am a friend of the Chinese people.
我是中国…
I am a friend...
人民的… 人民的…
of the Chinese... of the Chinese.
朋友 朋友
People People
对 我是安琪儿的朋友
Right I am a friend of Angel's
我是安琪儿的 最，最，最好的朋友
I am Angel's best friend.
是的
Yes.
做为军人，你们很勇敢 但有时，你们不珍惜生命
You are brave soldiers, but you don't value life
比如那天我和黑子打架 你们对投降…
Like the other day, I fought with Darkie...
而战争总会过去 活下去也是一种胜利
This war will end sooner or later Being alive is a victory.
所以我们有很多不同 风俗，观点什么的
We are very different.
但是，有一点相同
But we do have one thing in common.
都有爱
We have love.
爷爷，花花，黑子，还有你
Grandpa, Huahua, Darkie, and you
我看到你们的心里 都有许多的爱
I can see you all have a lot of love.
那就是黄河
That is the Yellow River.
是我们要去的地方
That is where we want to go.
美极了
It's beautiful.
安琪儿，我很久 就有个问题想问你
Angel, there is something I want to ask you
你为什么总把手榴弹
Why do you always...
捆在身上
have a grenade by you side?
对不起
Sorry
也许我不该问的
Maybe I shouldn't ask
没什么
Nothing
三炮啊，有啥儿信吗
Sanpao, any messages?
今天算我栽在你手里了
You win
是天数
It's destiny
只请你看在和我女儿 在一个营盘里共命的份上
My daughter worked with you
放过她的命
Please spare her
好，有种，是条汉子
Good, that's what a real man is
咱们俩一对一
It's one-on-one
咱俩家过去的仇 再杀多少年也到不了头
We are never able to settle the debt between our families
现在，咱们在队伍了 凡事都讲个理
But now we have to act reasonably
今儿个来，就是给你说个理的
I want to reason with you today
你说吧
Go ahead
就一句，你我都是中国人
We are both Chinese
鬼子杀了多少咱们多少老百姓
The Japs have killed so many Chinese
可人家大老远来 豁出命帮咱们打鬼子
He came all the way to help us fight the Japs
咱们还这么对待人家
And this is how we repay him?
你是江湖上闯了一辈子的 知道做人是最该讲个义字
You should know, we must do the right thing
人活一口气
That is what we live for
咱们无论怎样 都不能丢了中国人这个义字
We can not give the Chinese a bad name
再就是，我想告诉你 你女儿的事…
And I want to tell you about your daughter
不必
That's not necessary
你接着说
You go ahead
我俩在一个部队上 她的事知道一点儿
We are both is the army, I know a few things about her
但我不知道她和我是同乡 只知道她是城里来的学生娃儿
But I don't know we came from the same neighborhood, only that she is a student from the city
你知道她身上 为啥总捆着一颗手榴弹吗
Do you know why she always carries a grenade?
我是一个战士
I am a warrior
也是一个女人
I am also a woman
每一分钟都可能遇到危险
I could get into trouble anytime
会掉队，会被俘，会死亡
I could get lost, get caught or get killed
在死亡和被俘之间 做选择的时候
If I have to choose between death and captured
我们女人只能选择死亡
We women can only choose death.
因为我知道日本鬼子…
Because I know that the Japs...
是什么样的魔鬼
are devils.
我终于明白了
I finally understood
我面前的这个柔弱的中国女人 和她的同伴们
this dear Chinese girl standing in front of me
为什么能在这样恶劣的条件下 仍与日本正规军队作战
The Japanese have forced her and her countrymen to live
对入侵都的复仇
under terrible conditions
使他们宁可将自己和死亡 永远捆在一起
The Chinese would rather die fight the Japanese
宁可放弃生命 而不愿放弃人的尊严
than loose their dignity and live
你必须好好活下去
You have to stay alive
任何时候都不要失去勇气
Never get discouraged.
我们都会走过这个苦难的时代
We will get through the hardship.
将来你还有孩子
You will have your own children in the future.
像你
They will be as...
一样美
beautiful as you
我们寨主 明天又有一批货要过河
We have another cargo crossing the river tomorrow
还得请你多照应
Please take care of it
明天老地方
Same place tomorrow
满山的枣子火溜溜红
There are fruits all over the mountains
妹妹那个缝衣孤零零…
Little sister is sewing along...
妹妹缝衣你莫要针扎了手
Watch out don't hurt your fingers
哥哥我要舍你到那心头疼…
That will make me very sorry
寨主
Chief...
怎样
What?
收了
Let's go
您真的就这么把黑子给放了
You really let Darkie go?
十五的月亮，十六月
The moon is full
光棍棍的哥哥真后悔
I, being a bachelor, feeling very upset
明天我送你们过河
I take you cross the river tomorrow
但…我女儿得留下来
But... please let my daughter stay
该…给你成个家吧
It's time for you to get married
我自己的事情用不着别人来管
That's my business
就是黄河见了底，我也是你爹
Come what may, I am still your father
先生，她必须和我一起过河
Sir, she must go with me
她，是我女儿
She is my daughter
可是我爱她
But I love her
先生，你没病吧
You are not sick, are you?
我很清醒
I am sober
欧文先生
Mr. Owen
我的事谁也不能代替我决定
I am the only one who can decide my future
明天，渡口见
see you at the dock tomorrow.
日本人走了
The Japanese are gone.
他给咱准备了船
He got us a boat.
赵家和他安家十三代血仇
They are our sword enemies for 13 generations
他会坑咱
He cannot be trusted.
我感觉是谎话
I can feel that he is cheating.
不吹的是葫芦
He must be cheating
这是什么
What is this?
家啊
It's is home
家
Home
不，这怎么是家呢，这是洞
No, this is just a cave
家应该是…
Home should be...
这是花花
This is Huahua
还要有花
There should be flowers
对，还要有花
Right and flowers
安琪儿
Angel
我想当我们回去后 你就不再回军队了
When we go back, don't go back to the army
我带你飞回去
I will fly you back
完成你的学业
You can finish your study.
医科大学
Medical collage
对，我的服役期到了
right, and I will discharge from the army.
花
flowers
花很漂亮
Those flowers are beautiful.
这是我，像不像
This is me, does it look like me?
像，还有阿姨呢
Yes, and there is antie
对，还有阿姨
Right, and antie
安琪儿
Angel
我的同胞们还在作战
My people are still at war
我理解，但你已经…
I understand, but you have already...
在你的军队中服役五年了
served in the army for 5 years
服役期
Lag...
是的
Yes
别人把刀架在你头上的时候
But when someone is holding a knife against your neck
你就什么权利都没有了
You have no right
送给你用吧
You take it
但是…希望你早日 不再用这个东西
But I wish... you will never have to use it
我会在你身边保护你
I will protect you
我不允许在你身边 有死亡的存在
I won't allow you be threatened by death
你们听
Listen
黄河
It's the Yellow River
虽然安琪儿 给我讲过那么多次黄河
Angel talked a lot about the Yellow River
但当我真站在它面前的时候
Only then, as I stood on it's banks
仍被一种前所未有的震撼力 给征服了
did I understand its overwhelming strength and power
只有在这里，我才真正明白了
Only by standing by her, can one understand
为什么它被称做 中国人的母亲河
why they call it the mother river of China
为什么它是中国人 民族精神的象征
It is truly a symbol of the spirit of that nation
过了河，就快到家了
We are almost home
到家了
Home
过了这个山头，就是渡口了
When you cross the mountain, you will get to the dock
你还有胶卷吗
Is there any film left?
还有一张
One last photo
我想在这儿拍张照片
I would like to take a picture here
我很愿意
It's my pleasure
你能把照片给我吗
Can you give me the picture?
当然
Sure
你的，他们所有人的 我都会给你们
I will give you all your pictures
一定哦
That's a promise
一定
A promise
安琪儿
Angel
我爱你
I love you
都准备好了吗
Ready?
你就放心吧
Don't worry
船工呢
Where are the rowers?
在屋里
They are inside
寨主，我没有，我没有
Chief, I didn't...
日本人开的价更大，水涨船高 兄弟我只好…
The Japanese offered big money, so we...
你终于和我们站到一起了
You are finally by our side.
是啊，你们这也是为了 成全我啊
You are doing this for me
只要你女儿交出飞行员 我们保证既往不咎
We only want your daughter to turn the pilot in
事已至此，我也只能替我女儿 表示对你们的一点心意了
This I did for my daughter
兄弟，外面风大别吹着你了
Take care, it's cold outside.
红樱樱大马你肕上走
Get on your horses
妹妹送你到村头
Sister see you off
三年五载你要回家转
Please come back
莫忘情妹妹等得愁
Please remember that I am waiting for you
红樱樱大马我骑上走
I get on the big horse
三哥哥一路威风抖
Galloping all the way
明天回家看亲亲
Tomorrow I will be home
掀起妹妹的红盖头
To see my sweet heart
走
Let's go
去哪儿
Where to?
回野狼滩，我怕出叉 叫爷爷在那儿等我们
Back to the wolf beach, I told grandpa to wait for us there
爷爷
Grandpa
你俩快系上葫芦过河，我挡着
Take the calabashes and cross the river I will take care of them.
不，我要在这里
No, I am staying
黑子，别再跟我耍花招了
Darkie, don't play games with me.
老子早就盯上你们家老头啦
I have been watching your old man for quite some time.
有种的你出来，咱们刺刀上见
Come out like a man and fight.
黑子，咱们乡里乡亲的 把话说在头里
Darkie, let's get things straight.
只要把洋人交出来 日本人就答应放你俩走
Give us the American, the Japanese will let you go
快拉他过河，再晚就来不及了
Get him across the river before it's too late.
那你呢
What about you?
我水性好，慢慢能游过去
I can swim across.
我不会游泳
I can't swim.
我用梅子把我们连在一起 带你游过去
I can pull you
快点
Hurry
黑子，别打枪，你看看这是谁
Darkie, don't shoot, look who this is
快喊，叫你大啊 你大就在那头
Call your father, he is right there
大大
Daddy
快喊
Call him
哎，听见了
You hear
快喊
Hurry, call him
鬼子要交出洋大大
Japs want the foreign uncle
黑子，咱们都是中国人 犯得着为个洋人受罪吗
Darkie, we are both Chinese, why get into trouble for an American?
你也配是中国人
You don't deserve to be called a Chinese.
好，那就别怪我不讲情面了
Good, don't blame me then
大大…
Daddy
花花，大不能听鬼子的话 大是八路军
Huahua, Daddy cannot listen to the Japs Daddy is with the eighty rout army.
知道不
Do you know that?
知道
Yes
快下河
Go into the water.
哭
Cry
喊
Shout
再喊
One more time
你干什么
What are you doing?
不能让鬼子得到活口
We can not be captured alive.
不
No
不要打死我
Don't kill me
洋大大
Foreign uncle
还好，还好，你还没有弄坏它
Good, you have not broken it.
你们不是要活的我吗
Didn't you want to capture me alive?
开枪啊
Shoot me
你们不敢打死我
You dare not kill me
不敢
You don't dare
站住
Stop
再动
If you move
我就拉这个炸弹
I will pull
只要你们开枪打我
If you shoot me
我就拉这个炸弹
I will pull
你们不敢打死我
You bastard wouldn't shoot me
你们快下河
Quick, go into the river
我…过不了河了
I... can't
把枪和东西都留下
Leave the gun and your stuff
你们快下河
Quick, go into the water
胶卷你带着
You take the film
我们一起游过去
We are going to swim across the river together
快点
Come on
不要把我留给鬼子
Don't leave me to the Japs
把我带到黄河里去
Take me into the river
快点…
Come on...
我们永远在一起
We will be together forever
潜下去…
Down...
安琪儿
Angel
我很疼
It hurts so much
打到我背上了
they hit my back
抓紧我，坚持住 我们一定能过河
Hang on tight, we are going to cross this river
过了河…就要…到家了
When we cross the river, we can go home
快啊，到家了
Come on, we are almost home.
我们的家…
Our home...
Our home
我们的家…
安琪儿…
Angel...
她放弃了自己的生命 把生命留给了我们
My angel gave her life for us
她没有把自己的身体 留魔鬼面前
rather than surrender her pure body to the enemy
而是把身体还给了母亲河
She gave her self to the mother river
从她来到我面前的第一分钟起 我就已经感觉到了
I guess I knew it from the first time I laid eyes on her
她是上帝身边 最美丽的一个天使
She was the most beautiful thing that I have ever seen
我的安琪儿
An Angel
她引导我走出死亡
She delivered me from the darkness of death
也将引导我走向光明
And guided me into the light of life.
花花呢
Huahua, what about her?
到延安后我就回成都了
Afterwards, I was returned to Chiando
五十多年了 我不知道她在哪里
It's been over 50 years now
因为我只知道她叫花花
All I remember is she was called Huahua
但是我知道只要她还活着 就不会忘记这条河
But I know as long as she is alive, she will remember this river
这河里有她祖先的灵魂 还有…爱
Because it has love
能把照片给我吗
Can you give me the picture?
一定
It's a deal.